Minor E. Gordon, Ph.D.

Curriculum Vitae

cv256@minorgordon.net
https://mg4.consulting

Tulsa, OK 74114

Summary

I am a **software architect** and **full-stack software engineer** with 9 years of experience in industry. I specialize in building:

- complex web sites and web applications, such as Notablist.com
- software-as-a-service (SaaS) implementations
- programming tools, such as compilers and runtimes for domain-specific languages

I've worked on projects in a variety of domains, from supercomputing to the digital humanities. My strengths are a solid foundation in Computer Science, a range of hands-on skills, critical thinking, a systematic approach to new problems, attention to detail, high personal standards, a strong work ethic, and the ability to work autonomously.

Education

2009	Ph.D., Computer Science , University of Cambridge Dissertation: <u>Stage scheduling for CPU-intensive servers</u>
2005	Diplom Informatiker , Technische Universität Berlin Diplomarbeit: <u>Staged design for highly concurrent web servers</u>
2003	B.Sc., Computer Science, Oklahoma State University Tulsa

Projects

6/2017 – ongoing Full-stack development for Motivated Cognition experiment

Columbia University / New York, NY USA and remote

Motivated Cognition is a psychology research experiment investigating the effects of cognitive bias on our consumption of information online.

consumption of information offine

Activities Created a complete web application from a high-level specification, using TypeScript, Bootstrap,

Knockout.js, and webpack on the frontend; Java with microservices, YAML configuration, and MongoDB

persistence on the backend; Jenkins continuous integration; and Docker deployment

Generated code for models and services in TypeScript and Java

Integrated with Mechanical Turk for subject recruitment

4/2016 – ongoing Full-stack development for Polygon Analytics

Polygon Analytics Ltd. / Edinburgh, UK (remote only)

Activities Designed and implemented proprietary software in C++ and Python

9/2014 - ongoing Software architecture and full-stack development for the Notablist email newsletter search engine

New York, NY USA and remote

Notablist indexes millions of email newsletters from hundreds of thousands of publishers and provides both a search interface and real-time change alerts to users.

Activities <u>Backend prototyping in Python</u>:

Classified signup responses and mapped form inputs using numpy/scipy/scikit-learn

Backend production rewrite in Java:

· Generated Python JSON-RPC clients, Python command line tools, Java service interfaces and abstract

implementations, and Java JSON-RPC servlets from Thrift interface and data structure definitions

- Implemented Guice-injected Java micro-services that encapsulated MongoDB collections; ElasticSearch indices; Redis databases; S3 buckets; screenshotting and signups with Selenium; SpamAssassin checking; logstash queries; Stripe integration; Drip (CRM) integration; MailChimp, SparkPost, and SendGrid transactional email posting; etcd locking; DNS and whois querying and parsing; DMOZ category and Alexa and Quantcast rank lookups
- Designed and implemented a scalable distributed system for processing Common Crawl WARC records and submitting newsletter signups
- Created administrative user interface in Vaadin
- Set up Jenkins continuous integration
- · Deployed with Docker+Compose on real hardware

Frontend:

- Assumed responsibility for a three year-old Bootstrap+Backbone.js+Marionette.js code base in JavaScript
- Incrementally migrated code from JavaScript to TypeScript
- Added Selenium (Java) browser tests

7/2012 - ongoing Full-stack development of the TeraScript product suite

Tronics Software LLC / Stirling, NJ USA and remote

TeraScribe and TeraScript Server are a visual development environment and server-based runtime for TeraScript Action Files (TAFs), TeraScript Class Files (TCFs), and the TeraScript Markup Language (TML). TML is a markup-based web application language, similar in spirit to ColdFusion. TAF and TCF are ways of organizing TML.

Activities <u>TeraScript Server 8</u>:

Rewrote TeraScript 7 in Java while maintaining strict backwards compatibility:

- ANTLR-based compilers for TML and associated little languages
- Tree interpreters for TML, TAF, and TCF
- Versioned OSGi bundles with Maven and Apache Felix
- Library of standard functions, primitive types, and collections with extensive unit tests

<u>TeraScript Server 7</u> (formerly Witango Server):

Reorganized, cleaned up, and modernized a 17-year-old C++ code base and addressed numerous bugs and feature requests for the server's first major release in over two years; now in maintenance releases

Eliminated diverging platform-specific build systems (on Win32, Linux, and OS X) in favor of CMake and ported the code base to Win64 using Visual C++ 2012

Designed and implemented a SQL generator that visits dialect-specific trees of SQL-99 constructs

TeraScribe 8:

Reorganized and cleaned up a 10-year-old Java Swing code base in order to add a number of features to the code editor, including autocomplete and syntax highlighting, and refit the data source management interface to use JDBC metadata

Subcontracting:

Debugged production installations of TeraScript Server 7 and 8

Developed cross-platform (Android, iOS, Windows) mobile app prototype with Xamarin Forms and C#

4/2017 – 5/2017 Drug name comparison project

Activities

PSW Applied Research Inc. / Toronto, ON and remote

Implemented Kondrak's phonetic alignment and similarity algorithm (ALINE) and a bigram-based orthographic algorithm (BI-SIM) as a PostgreSQL C extension

Built a JavaScript demo application using jQuery and Bootstrap

4/2014 – 7/2014 Application development for the Muninn Project under contract to the Library and Archives Canada

PSW Applied Research Inc. / Toronto, ON and remote

Activities Created a command-line Java application for transcribing handwritten World War I medical records from

the Canadian Expeditionary Force (http://blog.muninn-project.org/node/79) using Amazon's Mechanical Turk crowdsourcing service: precut images for groups of lines, redundancy between workers, artificially-introduced mistakes and edit distances to detect cheating, and feedback to workers

3/2013 – 7/2013 Back end development for <u>Txtmrkt</u>, a marketplace for digital publications

Txtmrkt LLC / New York, NY USA and remote

Activities Designed and implemented a Model-View-Controller-based Java web application with Guice-injected

microservices backed by Amazon S3

Authenticated and authorized users with Shiro

Integrated co-branded order placement and payment notification with Amazon's Flexible Payments Service

12/2011 – 6/2012 Haystack: performance monitoring platform for online businesses

GrokIO LLC / New York, NY USA

Activities Designed an agent (Python) and manager (Java with Spring Security+MVC and Guice) architecture for gathering, storing, and querying time series data and metadata

Implemented time series databases from scratch using relational tables and memory-mapped files

Wrote RFC 3986 grammar-based URL and URN parsers using Ragel (Java) and pyparsing (Python)

Generated service interfaces in Java and Python with custom Protocol Buffers compiler plugins

Coded agent plugins in Java and Python for discovering and fetching metric metadata and data:

- Open source monitoring systems: Nagios, Ganglia, collectl, Graphite
- Open source server software: Apache httpd, nginx, MySQL, memcached, MongoDB, JMX
- Platform interfaces: procfs, sysctl, WMI, SNMP
- Third party APIs: Google Analytics, MailChimp, Spring Social, Amazon CloudWatch

Supervised user experience and graphic designers in Ukraine

Implemented a client-side user interface with the Google Web Toolkit, starting from wireframes:

- Architectural best practices: Model-View-Presenter; event bus; activities and places
- Custom widgets: date time range picker, cell table pager, search box, selection tree
- .war deployment to Tomcat with Maven

8/2011 – 12/2011 Back end development for <u>Birchbox</u>, a personalized subscription service for women's cosmetics samples

Birchbox Inc. / New York, NY, USA

Activities Designed, implemented, documented, and successfully deployed warehouse integration code in Java (back

end) and PHP (administrative front end)

Wrote a Thrift compiler and targets in Python+pyparsing to generate Java and PHP from Thrift definitions

Produced ad hoc business reports from MySQL using Java and Jython

5/2011 – 8/2011 Benchmarking server stacks in order to accurately provision EC2 instances at <u>Chartbeat</u>, a real-time web analytics software-as-a-service provider

Chartbeat Inc. / New York, NY, USA

Activities Synthesized a realistic benchmark for front-line web servers from statistical analyses of nginx access logs

Significantly reduced network bandwidth and latency on production servers with targeted optimizations

Wrote Python scripts for analyzing Ganglia RRDs, replaying HTTP request streams, harnessing httperfs

10/2010 – 4/2011 File I/O library for X10, a type-safe, parallel object-oriented language for high-productivity computing

IBM Research / Hawthorne, NY, USA

Activities Designed, implemented, tested, and documented a new low-overhead, buffer-based file library for X10:

- inspired by POSIX, FUSE, Boost.Filesystem, and Java NIO.2
- X10 and native code for the Java and C++ source-to-source compilation backends
- Scatter/gather I/O, aligned buffers, memory-mapped files, advisory locking

Microbenchmarked the X10 runtime

1/2009 – 7/2010 <u>LXFS</u>: fast and reliable data storage for High-Performance Computing clusters

NEC High Performance Computing Europe / Stuttgart, Germany

Activities Wrote Python and bash scripts for configuring, deploying, and administrating LXFS installations: Lustre

and lnet configuration (MGS, MDS, OSS, clients); redundant NFS exports; Nagios, Ganglia, and collectl monitoring; Heartbeat/Linux-HA services for failover; Promise RAID devices; network interfaces

(Infiniband, bonded Ethernet)

Finished two major LXFS releases, used in numerous deployments

Debugged and resolved issues in production parallel file systems

1/2009 – 7/2010 XtreemFS: a distributed and replicated file system for wide-area networks

NEC High Performance Computing Europe / Stuttgart, Germany

Activities Designed, implemented, and tested the XtreemFS userspace client:

- FUSE and Dokan (Windows FUSE-like library) interfaces
 Multiple pipelined ONC-RPC streams to a a single server
- Staged, event-driven concurrency for robust performance under load
- Close-to-open file caching with per-file page sizes
- Automatic failover between file replicas on timeout
- Heavily benchmarked under different I/O loads (iobench, dbench, metadata benchmarks)

Finished two major XtreemFS releases, both used in production

Collaborated with academic and industry partners in Europe, Israel, and China

Teaching Experience

2/2014 – 4/2014 SQL Fundamentals and Python Fundamentals workshops for Ph.D. students and post-doctoral

researchers in the natural sciences Iowa State University / Ames, IA USA

2002 – 2004 Technical supervision of Masters' theses

Oklahoma State University / Tulsa, OK USA

1/2002 – 3/2002 Mathematics tutoring for 6th and 7th graders

Tulsa Public Schools / Tulsa, OK USA

Computer Skills

Programming Java; Python; TypeScript; C++; C; SQL; C#; JavaScript

Frameworks Thrift; Protobufs; Guice; Guava; Shiro; ¡Query; Bootstrap; Knockout.js; Backbone.js

Databases ElasticSearch; MongoDB; Redis; SQLite; H2; SQL Server **Platforms** Windows; Debian- and RedHat-based Linux; OS X

IDEs and tools Visual Studio; Eclipse; Intelli]; Visual Studio Code; Maven; CMake

Revision control Git; Subversion

Personal

Languages English (native); German (fluent)

Hobbies Reading (history, biography, popular science); photography; Tai chi; open source software